Josue Baeza, Ph.D.

Scientific Investigator

GSK, Philadelphia, PA ☑ baezaj83@gmail.com in baezaj **y** baezaj83 baezaj **□** 0000-0003-4960-3905

Updated 2024-04-09

Qualifications and Research Interests

Highly productive analytical biochemist scientist, with 10^+ years in quantitative proteomics and protein biochemistry. A team player with strong leadership skills and a passion for mentoring. Biopharmaceutical experience focused on large molecule characterization for mid and late phase biopharm assets.

Technical Skills

Mass Spectrometry | Quantitative Proteomics | Data-independent acquisition (DIA) | Parallel reaction monitoring (PRM) | Data-dependent acquisition (DDA) | SILAC | pulsed-SILAC | TMT | Protein turnover | R | Bioconductor | Python | Machine Learning

Education

2011–2017 Ph.D., University of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, WI.

- Mechanisms of mitochondrial protein acetylation
- O PI: John M. Denu

2008–2010 B.S., University of Texas Permian Basin, Odessa, TX.

- O Purification of the human T-cell leukemia virus
- O PI: Tracie M. Gibson

Experience

Pharmaceutical

2021- **Investigator**, GSK, Philadelphia, PA.

- Present O Mass spectrometry characterization
 - O Large molecule characterization for mid and late phase development
 - O Host Cell Protein analysis
 - O Bioreactor proteomics support for Upstream Development

Research

2021 Johnson Foundation Fellow, Dept of Biochemistry & Biophysics, University of Pennsylvania.

- O Investigating the mechanisms of protein homeostasis during aging
- Managing a mass spectrometry facility

- 2017–2021 **Vice Provost Postdoctoral Fellow**, *Benjamin A. Garcia*, University of Pennsylvania.
 - Investigating the cross talk between protein turnover and epigenetics
 - O Quantifying histone post-translational modifications in health and disease
 - O Developing mass spectrometry-based proteomics technologies
 - Developing computational tools for mass spectrometry
- 2011–2017 **Graduate Research Assistant**, *John M. Denu*, University of Wisconsin-Madison.
 - Thesis aimed at understanding the mechanisms of mitochondrial protein acetylation
 - Developed a mass spectrometry-based method to quantify lysine acetylation stoichiometry
 - Coupled in vitro biochemistry methods with high resolution mass spectrometry technologies
 - O Determined second order rate constants for non-enzymatic acetylation

Internships

- 2011 INRO Postbaccalaureate Research Fellow, Shyam Kottilil, National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases.
 - O Determining genetic diversity of HCV genes in response to therapy
- 2010 INRO Summer Internship Research Fellow, Shyam Kottilil, National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases.
 - O Determined cytokine gene expression in HIV/HCV coinfection cell system
- 2008–2010 Undergraduate Research Assistant, Tracie M. Gibson, University of Texas Permian Basin.
 - O Applied biochemical techniques to purify the human T-cell leukemia virus (HTLV)

Awards and Honors

- Dec 2023 Exceptional Analytical Recognition Gold Award. GSK
- Dec 2022 Exceptional Analytical Recognition Silver Award. GSK
- Jan 2021 Rising Stars in Proteomics and Metabolomics: 40 under 40. Journal of Proteome Research
- Jun 2019 ASMS Postdoctoral Career Development Award. American Society for Mass Spectrometry
- May 2018 May Institute Computation and Statistics for Mass Spectrometry and Proteomics.

 May Institute
- Apr 2017 UPenn Vice Provost Postdoctoral Fellowship for Academic Diversity. University of Pennsylvania
- Jan 2015 AAAS/Science Program for Excellence in Science. University of Wisconsin-Madison
- Jun 2014 Journal of Biological Chemistry (JBC) Author Profile. Journal of Biological Chemistry
- Jun 2014 Dept of Biological Chemistry Travel Award. University of Wisconsin-Madison
- Jun 2012 National Science Foundation (NSF) Graduate Research Fellowship (GRFP). National Science Foundation

- Jan 2012 Honorable Mention The Why Files Cool Science Image http://tinyurl.com/NeuroFlare. University of Wisconsin-Madison
- Aug 2011 Molecular Biosciences Training Grant (NIH T32). University of Wisconsin-Madison
- Aug 2011 Science and Medicine Graduate Research Scholars Fellowship (SciMed GRS). University of Wisconsin-Madison
- Apr 2010 Xi Zeta Chapter Gamma Sigma Epsilon Chemistry Honor Society. University of Texas Permian Basin
- Feb 2010 National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID) Intramural Research Opportunities (INRO). National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases
- Jun 2009 University of Texas Louis Stokes Alliance for Minority Participation (UT-LSAMP) Summer Research Academy. University of Texas Permian Basin

Mentoring

- 2019–2024 Michael Gilbert, PhD student, University of Pennsylvania.
 - O Thesis: Investigating Caste Differences in Atta cephalotes
- 2018–2022 Richard Lauman, PhD student, University of Pennsylvania.
 - Thesis: Mass Spectrometry Methods for Studying RNA Modifications and RNA-Protein Interactions
- 2014–2016 **Keighley Reisenauer**, *Undergraduate student*, University of Wisconsin-Madison.
 - O Project: Measuring rates of non-enzymatic acetylation
 - O Protein purification and enzyme kinetics
- 2013–2016 **Nicole Rademacher**, *Undergraduate student*, University of Wisconsin-Madison.
 - O Project: Investigating mitochondrial protein acetylation
 - In vitro biochemistry

Academic Teaching

- 2019 Epigenetics, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA.
 - Guest Lecturer
 - Mass spectrometry analysis of histone proteins
- 2019 Intro to R workshops, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA.
 - O Intro to R: Data wrangling and visualization
 - Ongoing workshops teaching basic R
- 2017–2019 Introduction of Mass Spectrometry Based Proteomics, UPenn Epigenetics Institute, Philadelphia, PA.
 - O Annual workshops organized by UPenn Epigenetics Institute
 - Teaching fundamentals of mass spectrometry
- 2017–2019 Applied Proteomics, UPenn Epigenetics Institute, Philadelphia, PA.
 - O Second series of workshops hosted by the Epigenetics Institute
 - o overview of quantitative mass spectrometry
 - O Experimental design and statistics

- 2014 Introduction to Human Biochemistry (TA), University of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, WI.
 - organized tutoring sessions for pre-medical undergraduate students
- 2013 **Human Biochemistry (TA)**, University of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, WI.

 o organized tutoring sessions for pre-medical undergraduate students
- 2009 General Biology (TA), University of Texas Permian Basin, Odessa, TX.
 - O Biol 1307
 - O Teaching assistant for freshman biology students
- 2009 General Chemistry (TA), University of Texas Permian Basin, Odessa, TX.
 - Chem 1312
 - O Teaching assistant for freshman chemistry students
- 2008 Chemistry (TA), Odessa College, Odessa, TX.
 - Teaching assistant for chemistry students
- 2008 Advancement Via Individual Determination, Odessa High School, Odessa, TX
 - O AVID tutor for high school students

Publications

- 2024 Two DOT1 enzymes cooperatively mediate efficient ubiquitinindependent histone H3 lysine 76 tri-methylation in kinetoplastids, VS Frisbie, H Hashimoto, Y Xie, FNDL Vitorino, J Baeza, T Nguyen, Z Yuan, J Kiselar, BA Garcia, EW Debler, Nature Communications.
- 2024 In utero pulse injection of isotopic amino acids quantifies protein turnover rates during murine fetal development, J Baeza, BE Coons, Z Lin, J Riley, M Mendoza, WH Peranteau, BA Garcia, Cell Reports Methods.
- 2023 Histone chaperone HIRA, Promyelocytic Leukemia (PML) protein and p62/SQSTM1 coordinate to regulate inflammation during cell senescence and aging., N Dasgupta, X Lei, R Arnold, MG Teneche, KN Miller, A Rajesh, A Davis, V Anschau, AR Campos, R Gilson, A Havas, S Yin, ZM Chua, J Proulx, M Alcaraz, MI Rather, J Baeza, DC Schultz, SL Berger, PD Adams, bioRxiv.
- 2021 Improved SILAC quantification with data-independent acquisition to investigate bortezomib-induced protein degradation, LK Pino, J Baeza, R Lauman, B Schilling, BA Garcia, Journal of proteome research.
- 2021 Sex-specific effects of in vitro fertilization on adult metabolic outcomes and hepatic transcriptome and proteome in mouse, L Narapareddy, EA Rhon-Calderon, LA Vrooman, J Baeza, DK Nguyen, C Mesaros, Y Lan, BA Garcia, RM Schultz, MS Bartolomei, FASEB journal: official publication of the Federation of American Societies

- 2021 Self-acetylation at the active site of phosphoenolpyruvate carboxykinase (PCK1) controls enzyme activity, P Latorre-Muro, J Baeza, R Hurtado-Guerrero, T Hicks, I Delso, C Hernandez-Ruiz, A Velazquez-Campoy, AJ Lawton, Jus Angulo, JM Denu, JeA Carrodeguas, Journal of Biological Chemistry.
- 2020 Revealing dynamic protein acetylation across subcellular compartments, J Baeza, AJ Lawton, J Fan, MJ Smallegan, I Lienert, T Gandhi, OM Bernhardt, L Reiter, JM Denu, Journal of proteome research.
- 2020 Sex-specific effects of in vitro fertilization on adult metabolic phenotypes and hepatic transcriptomic and proteomic pathways in mouse, L Narapareddy, EA Rhon-Calderon, LA Vrooman, J Baeza, DK Nguyen, Y Lan, BA Garcia, RM Schultz, MS Bartolomei, bioRxiv.
- 2019 The E3 ligase adaptor molecule SPOP regulates fetal hemoglobin levels in adult erythroid cells, X Lan, E Khandros, P Huang, SA Peslak, SK Bhardwaj, JD Grevet, O Abdulmalik, H Wang, CA Keller, B Giardine, J Baeza, ER Duffner, OE Demerdash, XS Wu, CR Vakoc, BA Garcia, RC Hardison, J Shi, GA Blobel, Blood Advances.
- 2019 Deep profiling and custom databases improve detection of proteoforms generated by alternative splicing, LM Agosto, MR Gazzara, CM Radens, S Sidoli, J Baeza, BA Garcia, KW Lynch, Genome research.
- 2019 Site-specific lysine acetylation stoichiometry across subcellular compartments, AJ Lindahl, AJ Lawton, J Baeza, JA Dowell, JM Denu, Protein Acetylation: Methods and Protocols.
- 2018 Dynamic acetylation of phosphoenolpyruvate carboxykinase toggles enzyme activity between gluconeogenic and anaplerotic reactions, *P*Latorre-Muro, *J* Baeza, *EA* Armstrong, *R* Hurtado-Guerrero, *F* Corzana, *LE*Wu, *DA* Sinclair, *P* Lopez-Buesa, *JA* Carrodeguas, *JM* Denu, Molecular cell.
- 2018 Quantifying dynamic protein acetylation using quantitative stoichiometry, J Baeza, AJ Lawton, J Fan, MJ Smallegan, I Lienert, T Gandhi, OM Bernhardt, L Reiter, JM Denu, AG Biognosys, Preprint at https://www.biorxiv.org/content/.
- 2017 Scalable and purification-free synthesis of a myristoylated fluorogenic sirtuin substrate, I Galleano, J Nielsen, AS Madsen, CA Olsen, Synlett.

- 2016 Mechanisms and dynamics of protein acetylation in mitochondria, J Baeza, MJ Smallegan, JM Denu, Trends in biochemical sciences.
- 2016 Investigating histone acetylation stoichiometry and turnover rate, J Fan, J Baeza, JM Denu, Methods in Enzymology.
- 2015 Site-specific reactivity of nonenzymatic lysine acetylation, J Baeza, MJ Smallegan, JM Denu, ACS chemical biology.
- 2014 Stoichiometry of Site-specific Lysine Acetylation in an Entire Proteome*?, J Baeza, JA Dowell, MJ Smallegan, J Fan, D Amador-Noguez, Z Khan, JM Denu, Journal of Biological Chemistry.
- 2013 Activation of the Protein Deacetylase SIRT6 by Long-chain Fatty Acids and Widespread Deacylation by Mammalian Sirtuins*?, JL Feldman, J Baeza, JM Denu, Journal of Biological Chemistry.
- 2012 Rapid identification of ESKAPE bacterial strains using an autonomous microfluidic device, JY Ho, NJ Cira, JA Crooks, J Baeza, DB Weibel, PLoS One.
- 2012 Human immunodeficiency virus enhances hepatitis C virus replication by differential regulation of IFN and TGF family genes, X Zhang, M Daucher, J Baeza, C-W Kim, R Russell, S Kottilil, Journal of medical virology.

Selected Research Talks

- Aug 2023 Quantitative proteomics to characterize the cell culture process in drug substance development, Chinese American Society for Mass Spectrometry (CASMS), Online.
- Jun 2020 Applications of Skyline for Method Development and Quantification of Histone PTMs, Skyline User Group Meeting, Online.
- Jun 2019 Quantitative analysis of the fetal tissue translatome reveals temporal and tissue-specific regulatory networks in utero, American Society for Mass Spectrometry, Atlanta, GA.
- Mar 2018 Quantifying protein synthesis rates during fetal development reveals temporal and tissue specific regulatory networks, *US Human Proteome Organization*, Minneapolis, MN.

Selected Posters

- Oct 2020 A robust and flexible method for quantifying protein turnover rates across an entire proteome, US Human Proteome Organization Connect, Online.
- Mar 2019 Quantitative analysis of the fetal tissue translatome by mass spectrometry reveals temporal and tissue-specific regulatory networks in utero, US Human Proteome Organization, Washington DC.
- Sep 2018 Quantifying the fetal tissue translatome reveals temporal and tissue specific regulatory networks during development, Human Proteome Organization, Orlando, FL.
- Jun 2017 Acetylation stoichiometry analysis of the Sirt3 deficient liver, American Society for Mass Spectrometry, San Antonio, TX.
- Jun 2015 Site specific reactivity of non-enzymatic lysine acetylation, American Society for Mass Spectrometry, St. Louis, MO.
- Dec 2014 Site specific reactivity of non-enzymatic lysine acetylation, American Society for Cell Biology, Philadelphia, PA.
- Jun 2014 Stoichiometry of acetylation in an entire proteome, American Society for Mass Spectrometry, Minneapolis, MN.

- Aug 2013 Stoichiometry of acetylation determined by isotopic modification and mass spectrometry, Molecular Biosciences Training Grant Retreat, Madison, WI.
- Sep 2011 MicroRNA expression profiling identifies potential anti-viral targets in HCV-infected human hepatoma cells, International Symposium on Hepatitis C Virus, Seattle, WA.
- Aug 2010 Determining hepatitis C virus diversity and evolution during antiviral therapy using quantitative deep sequencing, NIH Summer Research Program Poster Day, Bethesda, MD.
- Feb 2010 Purification of the human T-cell leukemia virus type-1 virion using sucrose density gradient ultracentrifugation, American Association for the Advancement of Science, San Diego, CA.

Committee and Research Group Membership

- 2021 Committee Member, Proteomics Standards Research Group (sPRG), Associ-Present ation of Biomolecular Resources Facilities (ABRF).
 - To design and develop performance standards and resources for mass spectrometrybased proteomic applications

Professional Organizations

- 2021 American Biomolecular Resources Facilities (ABRF).
- 2017 Human Proteome Organization (HUPO).
- 2017 US Human Proteome Organization (US HUPO).
- 2014 American Society for Cell Biology (ASCB).
- 2013 American Society for Mass Spectrometry (ASMS).
- 2010 American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS).